Use
Global Events
The following events are as the name implies, global. The scripts are therefore predefined. To use a global script, simply create the relevant script file and place it in data/scripts. 

loading.c

loading screen
value:current loading progree
max:max entity to be loaded


endlevel.c
Any level ends. 

join#.c
Corresponding player# (1-4) joins a game in progress. 

key#.c
Corresponding player# (1-4) presses or releases a key. 

keyall.c
Any player presses or releases a key. 

player: Player index (0-3). 
level.c
Any level begins. 
pdie#.c
Corresponding player# (1-4) dies. 

respawn#.c
Corresponding player# (1-4) respawns after death. 

score#.c
Score changes for corresponding player# (1-4). 

timetick.c
Each tick of the game timer. 

time: Current time value. 
update.c
Engine starts update cycle. 

updated.c
Engine completes update cycle. 

Level Events
Level events are tied to a specific level. To define a level script, add the desired event into the level.txt, followed by a path to the script file. 

keyscript#
Corresponding player# (1-4) presses or releases a key during this level. 

player: Player index (0-3). 
spawnscript
Entity is spawned into play. This script is defined on a spawn by spawn basis (similar to Alias or Health), and a single spawn may have multiple spawnscripts if desired. 

self: Caller. 
Entity Events
The following events are all entity specific. To define an entity event script, add the desired event name into the model header, followed a path to the script file. 

animationscript
Entity changes animation frame. 

self: Caller. 
animnum: Animation ID. 
frame: Animation frame. 
Animation scripts are a bit unique in that there is no need to include a main() function. Instead, you may add functions to be executed on call, or insert code directly into model files as shown below: 

@script ... @end_script - These two commands are used in tandem; by placing them directly within a model's animations you can insert script. You cannot define functions within the script insert as it is parsed to part of a function main(), but you can execute functions already defined. Note that regardless of which frame in the animation @script/@end_script tags are placed, the code will be evaluated on every frame. 

anim freespecial#

    frame data/chars/model/exam0001.png
@script
    This code will be run on each frame of the animation...
@script_script
    frame data/chars/model/exam0002.png
    frame data/chars/model/exam0003.png
@cmd {name} {argument1} {argument2}... - This command will parse the expression into a function call, like name(argument1, argument2, ....). The function can either be a system function or user defined function. This means you can define functions in the animation script file, and then execute it here. @cmd is evaluated once when the animation frame immediately following the tag is reached. Multiple @cmd tags may be used. 

Notice: Arguments may not have spaces, use _ instead. If it is a string, enclose it with quotes: "thevalue". 

anim freespecial#

    frame data/chars/model/exam0001.png
@cmd function                               #Run this function on next frame (exam0002).   
    frame data/chars/model/exam0002.png
@cmd another_function  3 "string argument"  #Run this function on next frame (exam0003).
@cmd another_function2 1                    #Run this function on next frame as well (exam0003).
    frame data/chars/model/exam0003.png
didblockscript
Entity successfully blocks incoming attack. 

self: Caller. 
attacker: Entity attempting attack. 
damage: Amount of intended damage. 
attacktype: Type of damage. 
drop: Knockdown power of damage. 
attacktype: attack type, see 'openborconstant'. 
noblock: block break force of attack. 
guardcost: Guardcost of attack. 
jugglecost: Jugglecost of attack. 
pauseadd: Pause value of attack. 
didhitscript
Entity's attack box makes contact with another entity's bbox, or entity is an item type being retrieved. 

self: Caller. 
damagetaker: Recipient of attack or item. 
damage: attack damage. 
"drop: knockdown power. 
attacktype: attack type, see 'openborconstant'. 
noblock: block break force of attack. 
guardcost: Guardcost of attack. 
jugglecost: Jugglecost of attack. 
pauseadd: Pause value of attack. 
blocked: Receiving entity did (1) or did not (0) block attack. 
keyscript
Player controlling this entity presses or releases a key. 

self: Caller. 
player: Player index (0-3). 
onblockascript
Each update while entity is prevented from moving upward through platform (i.e. "hitting head"). 

self: Caller. 
obstacle: Entity blocking caller. 
onblockoscript
Each update while entity is prevented from moving through obstacle entity. 

self: Caller. 
obstacle: Entity blocking caller. 
onblocksscript
Each update while entity is prevented from moving through screen boundary. 

self: Caller. 
onblockwscript
Each update while entity is prevented from moving through wall. 

self: Caller. 
plane: Plane of movement blocked. 
1 = X 
2 = Z 
height: Height of blocking wall. 
onblockzscript
Each update while entity is blocked by the Z boundary. 

self: Caller. 
ondeathscript
Immediately after takedamage when incoming damage is sufficient to kill entity. 

self: Caller. 
attacker: Entity causing damage. 
damage: Amount of unmodified damage. 
attacktype: Type of damage. 
drop: Knockdown power of damage. 
attacktype: attack type, see 'openborconstant'. 
noblock: block break force of attack. 
guardcost: Guardcost of attack. 
jugglecost: Jugglecost of attack. 
pauseadd: Pause value of attack. 
onfallscript
Entity is put into fall state. Fires immediately after engine applies normal fall values. 

self: Caller. 
attacker: Entity causing knockdown. 
damage: Amount (if any) of unmodified damage at time of knockdown. 
drop: Knockdown power of attack instigating fall. 
attacktype: attack type, see 'openborconstant'. 
noblock: block break force of attack. 
guardcost: Guardcost of attack. 
jugglecost: Jugglecost of attack. 
pauseadd: Pause value of attack. 
onmovexscript
Each update while entity is moving along X axis. 

self: Caller. 
onmovezscript
Each update while entity is moving along Z axis. 

self: Caller. 
onmoveascript
Each update while entity is moving along Y axis. 

self: Caller. 
onspawnscript
Entity is spawned into play. Note that if entity also has a level spawn script, this script runs first. 

self: Caller. 
thinkscript
Each time entity AI "thinks". This doesn't happen on every update; only on some of them. Used to expand on or override the engine's AI. 

self: Calling entity. 
script
Each time engine updates entity. Update does not refer to an actual change. Entities are internally updated on every engine cycle. 

self: Calling entity. 
takedamagescript
Entity receives damage from any source. 

self: Caller. 
attacker: Entity causing damage. 
damage: Amount of unmodified damage. 
attacktype: Type of damage. 
drop: Knockdown power of damage. 
noblock: block break force of attack. 
guardcost: Guardcost of attack. 
jugglecost: Jugglecost of attack. 
pauseadd: Pause value of attack. 
Notes
Key Scripts
Key scripts can be extremely powerful, but if not used properly will prove equally frustrating. Keep in mind the following when creating your key scripts: 

First, it is important to remember that key scripts fire both on press AND release of a key. This means a single key press actually runs a given keyscript twice; once when a player presses the key and again when he/she lets go. Make sure to account for this in your scripts or you will receive unexpected results. The playerkeys() function allows easy differentiation between press or release. 

Another consideration is to know the order in which key events run. If you have multiple key scripts overlapping each other, it is vital to know and account for the order in which the engine will process each. From first to last: 

1. Level keyscript# 
2. Entity keyscript 
3. Global key#.c 
4. Global keyall.c 
5. Default key action. 
Another facet to keep in mind is the use of AI Flags and the takeaction() function. Without them the engine may override your scripted command milliseconds before it has a chance to occur. A common example would be trying to execute a custom attack while walking. Simply setting your desired animation won't be enough because the engine will set the walk animation right back. But by including the correct caveat functions in your script, the engine will "wait" and execute the desired actions properly. 

While fairly obvious, you should keep in mind the key event itself should be canceled when you are finished with it. Otherwise the engine will still run the key's default action immediately after all key scripts are complete. While in rare cases this might be useful, in most it will at best override your intended action and at worse produce a bug or crash. 

Examples
Entity Scripts
The model below has numerous scripts defined that dramatically increase its features and functionality. 

...
blockpain       1 
sleepwait       1000
combostyle      1
atchain         1 2 3 4 0 5 6 7

#*****Scripts*****
keyscript 		data/chars/andy/scripts/key.c
animationscript 	data/scripts/com0001.c
didblockscript  	data/scripts/bloc0001.c
takedamagescript	data/scripts/dama0001.c 
didhitscript		data/scripts/hit0001.c
onmovezscript		data/scripts/movz0001.c
onspawnscript		data/scripts/movz0001.c 

#*****MP Specific*****
mpset 100 3 50 1 2 2				
...
